<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" xmlns:aid5="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/5.0/" xmlns:dcr="http://www.isocat.org/ns/dcr" xmlns:loext="urn:org:documentfoundation:names:experimental:office:xmlns:loext:1.0" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators" xmlns:mets="http://www.loc.gov/METS/" xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xhtml="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml/strict" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" lock="ndufournaud" time="2021-07-12T16:52:54.988+02:00" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://www.ehess.fr/crh/schemas/savoirs.xsd" xml:id="CMA_1_Vartejanu">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">The Letter as Object</title>
        <title type="sub">The Written Word between Reification and
        Hermeneutics in Rabbinic Judaism</title>
        <author role="aut">
          <forename>Madalina</forename>
          <surname>Vârtejanu-Joubert</surname>
          <affiliation>Centre d’études juives, EHESS Paris et Centre
          Gustave-Glotz</affiliation>
          <idno type="IDREF">080825117</idno>
        </author>
        <funder>EHESS</funder>
        <principal>Projet Savoirs</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>encodage et supervision</resp>
          <name xml:id="ND">
            <forename>Nicole</forename>
            <surname>Dufournaud</surname>
          </name>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>supervision</resp>
          <name xml:id="ALR">
            <forename>Axel</forename>
            <surname>Le Roy</surname>
          </name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Seconde édition numérique, Paris, <date when="2021">2021</date> dans le cadre du projet Savoirs.</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <distributor>EHESS</distributor>
        <address>
          <addrLine>54 bd Raspail</addrLine>
          <addrLine>75006 Paris</addrLine>
          <addrLine>FRANCE</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/deed.fr">Creative
          Commons Attribution</licence>
          <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/fr/">Creative
          Commons - Attribution - Pas d’Utilisation Commerciale - Pas de
          Modification 3.0 non transposé - CC BY-NC-ND 3.0</licence>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct corresp="http://zotero.org/groups/2408090/items/RDXFAMIN" type="journalArticle" xml:lang="fre">
          <analytic>
            <title level="a">The Letter as Object. The Written Word between
            Reification and Hermeneutics in Rabbinic Judaism</title>
            <idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.4000/mondesanciens.129</idno>
            <author>
              <forename>Madalina</forename>
              <surname>Vârtejanu-Joubert</surname>
            </author>
          </analytic>
          <monogr>
            <title level="j">Cahiers « Mondes anciens ». Histoire et
            anthropologie des mondes anciens</title>
            <idno type="ISSN">2107-0199</idno>
            <editor>
              <forename>Renée</forename>
              <surname>Koch-Piettre</surname>
            </editor>
            <editor>
              <forename>Christophe</forename>
              <surname>Batsch</surname>
            </editor>
            <imprint>
              <biblScope unit="volume">Écritures rituelles</biblScope>
              <biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
              <date>2010</date>
              <note type="accessed">2020-04-05T17:13:43Z</note>
              <note type="url">http://journals.openedition.org/mondesanciens/129</note>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>
        <p>« Savoirs » est une plateforme de publication numérique vouée à
        l’histoire et à l’anthropologie des sciences et des savoirs. Le projet
        est porté par l’EHESS (Paris) avec le soutien de différents
        partenaires. Plus qu’une revue, une archive d’articles ou une
        collection de livres, il s’agit d’une bibliothèque « intelligente » et
        expérimentale qui propose des parcours de lecture heuristiques et
        réflexifs entre les textes, grâce à différents algorithmes de
        recherche et de suggestions reposant notamment sur un balisage des
        lieux, des dates et des concepts en XML-TEI.</p>
      </projectDesc>
      <appInfo>
        <application ident="metopes-savoirs" version="1.0">
          <label>Métopes</label>
          <label>Savoirs</label>
          <desc>Environnement de transformation, d’édition et d’annotation
          XML-TEI-Savoirs (XMLMind-XMLEditor Pro 7.6.)</desc>
          <ref target="www.metopes.fr"/>
        </application>
        <application ident="certic" version="1.0">
          <label>PluCo</label>
          <desc>Plugin d’édition XML collaborative pour le logiciel
          XMLMind-XMLEditor</desc>
          <ref target="http://www.unicaen.fr/recherche/mrsh/document_numerique/outils/pluco"/>
        </application>
      </appInfo>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="geonames">
          <desc>
            <ref target="https://www.geonames.org/"/>GeoNames : base de
          données géographique</desc>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="idref">
          <desc>
            <ref target="https://idref.fr/"/>IdRef : Identifiants et
          Référentiels pour l'enseignement supérieur et la recherche</desc>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="savoirs">
          <desc>
            <ref target="http://datu.ehess.fr"/>Thésaurus Savoirs</desc>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="zotero">
          <desc>
            <ref target="https://www.zotero.org/"/>Zotero : gestionnaire
          de références Savoirs</desc>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="langISO">
          <desc>
            <ref target="http://www.loc.gov/standards/iso639-2/"/>ISO
          639-2 : Codes pour la représentation des noms de langues</desc>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng"/>
      </langUsage>
      <!--Mots clefs proposés dans la source par l’auteur-->
      <textClass>
        <keywords resp="auteur" scheme="keyword" xml:lang="eng">
          <list>
            <item>rabbinic script</item>
            <item>rabbinic scripture</item>
            <item>rabbinic hermeneutics</item>
            <item>script and word reification</item>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <!--Mots clefs proposés par l’annoteur à partir du Thésaurus Savoirs-->
      <textClass>
        <keywords>
          <term/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <!--Lieux principaux proposés dans la source-->
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="geonames">
          <term/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <!--Dates proposées dans la source-->
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="_temp">
          <term/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2019-07-30T13:18:00" who="Agnès">Révision</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="text">
    <front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart type="main">The Letter as Object</titlePart>
          <titlePart type="sub">The Written Word between Reification and
          Hermeneutics in Rabbinic Judaism<note n="1" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn1">
              <p>My special thanks are addressed to Dana Mihailescu from the
              University of Bucharest, who provided the English version of
              this paper.</p>
            </note>
          </titlePart>
        </docTitle>
        <byline>
          <docAuthor>Madalina Vârtejanu-Joubert</docAuthor>
          <affiliation>Centre d’études juives, EHESS Paris et Centre
          Gustave-Glotz</affiliation>
        </byline>
      </titlePage>
      <div type="abstract">
        <p xml:lang="eng">My attempt is to answer the question of “the
        pragmatic contexts within which the authority of writing is
        established”. This authority is double in the case of Judaism as what
        is “written” and, starting with a particular moment in history, as the
        act of “writing”. Starting with the Second Temple, the Torah is sacred
        as “word” and “scroll” at the same time as it is sacred by means of
        its content and as an object. The history of Judaism will be
        constantly characterized by this double simultaneous sacredness.
        According to the scholar literature, this phenomenon has been unique
        in the Mediterranean and Middle Eastern worlds ever since the end of
        Antiquity. At the time, two new book cultures were born almost
        simultaneously: that of emergent Christianity and that of Judaism in
        change. I think that drawing attention to this novelty will help us to
        one day explain this phenomenon, even if at present there is no
        hypothesis in relation to Judaism. The rationalisation of this double
        sacredness in the rabbinical texts consists in the hermeneutical
        valorisation of material aspects. But, on the other hand, the
        hermeneutical enterprise makes use of procedures for the reification
        of writing; hence ensue a whole array of discussions on the form of
        letters and the meaning of that form. We are witnessing there a double
        phenomenon: the “textualisation” of reality and the “reification” of
        the text.</p>
        <p xml:lang="fre">Comme l’affirme l’argumentaire de la journée d’étude
        sur « Écritures rituelles », l’écriture est généralement associée à
        l’oralité et étudiée à la lumière de la coupure cognitive énoncée et
        théorisée par Jack Goody, théorie qui a donné naissance au domaine des
        « literacy studies ». L’approche choisie est de mettre face à face non
        pas « écrit » et « oral » mais « écriture » et « rituel ». Dans le
        judaïsme le « faire » n’a jamais été absent, ni de la religion, ni de
        l’historiographie : il n’est pas question ici de réhabiliter cette
        notion dans le judaïsme. Par contre, ce qui me semble intéressant est
        d’interroger les rapports entre « écrit », « écriture » et « rituel ».
        Je reprends ici la distinction faite par les concepteurs du programme,
        entre « écrit » et « écriture », où cette dernière et entendue comme
        « le tracé même saisi dans son exécution au cours d’une opération
        rituelle ». Autrement dit, la notion de « rituel » est entendue comme
        déjà incluse dans celle d’« écriture » et la tension fertile pour
        l’étude est celle entre le « contenu » et la « forme », ou entre « le
        sens de ce qui est écrit » et les aspects matériels qui le
        conditionnent. Nous essayons ainsi de répondre à la question lancée
        dans le même argumentaire : « les conditions pragmatiques dans
        lesquelles s’élabore l’autorité de l’écriture ». Dans le judaïsme
        cette autorité est double : celle de l'« écrit » et, à partir d’un
        certain moment dans l’histoire, celle de l'« écriture ». À partir du
        Second Temple, la Torah est sacrée à la fois comme « parole » et comme
        « rouleau », à la fois de par son contenu et en tant qu’objet.
        L’histoire du judaïsme sera constamment traversée par cette double
        sacralité simultanée. Selon la littérature de spécialité, ce phénomène
        est unique dans le monde méditerranéen et moyen-oriental de la fin de
        l’Antiquité. À cette époque, à peu près simultanément, deux nouvelles
        cultures du livre voient le jour : celle du christianisme naissant et
        celle du judaïsme en mutation. Je crois que le fait de souligner cette
        nouveauté nous aidera un jour à expliquer ce phénomène, même si pour
        l’heure en ce qui concerne le judaïsme il n’existe aucune hypothèse.
        La rationalisation, à travers les textes rabbiniques, de cette double
        sacralité consiste en une mise en valeur herméneutique des aspects
        matériels. Mais d’autre part, l’entreprise herméneutique fait appel à
        des procédés de réification de l’écriture, d’où un ensemble de
        discussions sur la forme des lettres et la signification de cette
        forme. Nous assistons ainsi à un double phénomène : celui de la
        « textualisation » de la réalité et celui de « réification » du texte.
        Cet aspect est observable à plusieurs niveaux et se concrétise sur
        plusieurs plans. Je vais mentionner trois de ces niveaux de ce que je
        considère être une réification du texte : le premier est le texte de
        la Torah comme objet sacré ; le deuxième est la forme d’exégèse
        biblique qui est le midrach, technique qui fait exploser l’unité de
        sens habituelle qui est la phrase ou le mot, pour en utiliser les
        parties ainsi obtenues comme une boîte à outils (cf. <hi rend="italic" style="typo_Italique">gematria</hi>, <hi rend="italic" style="typo_Italique">notarikon,</hi> la forme des lettres) ; le
        troisième niveau concerne la lettre même (cf. les ornements afférents
        à certaines lettres). Cette catégorisation n’est probablement ni
        exhaustive, ni suffisamment pertinente mais mon propos n’est pas de la
        développer ici ; je voulais simplement situer les exemples que je vais
        analyser par la suite dans un contexte plus large de l’imaginaire
        religieux juif.</p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div type="chapitre" xml:id="mainDiv">
        <div type="section1" xml:id="d1e87">
          <head subtype="level1" xml:id="d1e88">Introduction</head>
          <p xml:id="d1e90">Writing is usually associated with the oral and is
          studied in light of the cognitive gap coined and theorized by
          <persName ref="026897180" type="idref" xml:base="https://www.idref.fr/">Jack Goody</persName> in a theory
          which has determined the emergence of “literacy studies”. My
          approach for the present paper is not to confront “the written” and
          “the oral” but “writing” and “ritual”. In the case of Judaism,
          “agency” has never been absent from either religion or
          historiography: thus, my object here is not that of rehabilitating
          this notion within Judaism. On the contrary, what I find of
          particular interest is the possibility to test the relations between
          “the written”, the act of “writing” and “the ritual”. I resume here
          the distinction between “the written” and the act of “writing” that
          was made by the program’s designers, in which the latter term is
          understood as “the layout itself as seized in its execution during a
          ritual operation”. To put it differently, the notion of “ritual” is
          already contained within that of “writing” and the fertile tension
          to be pursued in one’s analysis is that between “content” and
          “form”, between “the written meaning” and the material aspects which
          condition it. Therefore, my attempt is to answer the question
          launched by the “Avant-propos” : “the pragmatic contexts within
          which the authority of writing is established”. This authority is
          double in the case of Judaism as what is “written” and, starting
          with a particular moment in history, as the act of “writing”.
          Starting with the Second Temple, the Torah is sacred as “word” and
          “scroll” at the same time as it is sacred by means of its content
          and as an object. The history of Judaism will be constantly
          characterized by this double simultaneous sacredness. According to
          the scholar literature, this phenomenon has been unique in the
          Mediterranean and Middle Eastern worlds ever since the end of
          Antiquity. At the time, two new book cultures were born almost
          simultaneously : that of emergent Christianity and that of Judaism
          in change. I think that drawing attention to this novelty will help
          us to one day explain this phenomenon, even if at present there is
          no hypothesis in relation to Judaism.</p>
          <p xml:id="d1e92">The rationalisation of this double sacredness in
          the rabbinical texts consists in the hermeneutical valorisation of
          material aspects. But, on the other hand, the hermeneutical
          enterprise makes use of procedures for the reification of writing ;
          hence ensue a whole array of discussions on the form of letters and
          the meaning of that form. In that, we are witnessing a double
          phenomenon : the “textualisation” of reality and the “reification”
          of the text.<note n="2" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn2">
              <p>Colette Sirat describes the process as follows : “The Sefer
              Torah has become the Sanctuary where God resides. Henceforth,
              the divine word gets embodied in the visible letters, it is no
              longer just <hi rend="italic">miqra</hi>, what the ear can hear,
              but also and in particular what the eye can grasp. [...] The
              idea that the Torah is made up of letters, not of sounds, runs
              throughout the entire history of Jewish thought.” (Sirat 1991,
              p. 432, my translation)</p>
            </note>
          </p>
          <p xml:id="d1e100">This aspect can be observed and materializes
          itself on different levels. I will mention three levels of what I
          consider to be a case of textual reification: first comes the text
          of the Torah as a sacred object; the second level is the form of
          biblical exegesis represented by the midrash, a technique which
          explodes the usual unity of signification — the sentence or the
          word — in order to use the parts thus obtained as one would use a
          toolbox (see <hi rend="italic">gematria</hi>, <hi rend="italic">notarikon</hi>, the form of letters) ; the third level
          refers to the letter itself (see the ornaments pertaining to certain
          letters). Probably this categorisation is neither exhaustive nor
          pertinent enough but my interest is not that of developing it ; I
          only want to provide a larger scope than the Jewish religious
          imaginary for the examples which I will analyse in what follows.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section1" xml:id="d1e108">
          <head subtype="level1" xml:id="d1e109">The Scroll</head>
          <p xml:id="d1e111">Let us start by what I have called the first
          level of reification, which concerns the scroll, the book as an
          easily perceptible object. In fact, it is possible that the process
          of canonizing a text ran parallel to that of its sacralisation as an
          object. Nevertheless, by contrast, if the opinions on the “knowledge
          of the Torah” were frequently present in the writings of the Second
          Temple, the idea of “material conformity” and its binding rules only
          appear in the Mishna. The first indications of the ritual conformity
          of a Torah scroll can be found in the tractate Meguilla, especially
          in the commentaries of the Gemara. I will return to that. This
          tradition develops so extensively in later periods that the Talmud
          will include a minor tractate of the “Scribes”, Massekhet Sopherim,
          dating back to the eighth century.</p>
          <p xml:id="d1e113">Undoubtedly getting their inspiration from the
          juridical sphere, Rabbis rationalize the idea of conformity by means
          of the injunction “not to add or subtract anything” (Eruvin 13a).
          The phrase finds support in the deuteronomical verse “You will keep
          and practice all I command without adding or subtracting anything”
          (Dt 13.1). Rabbis have always interpreted that verse in reference to
          a scribal activity. According to the rabbis, if we ignore that
          commandment we expose the entire Universe to the threat of
          extinction.</p>
          <p xml:id="d1e115">Yet scribes are aware that they make <hi rend="italic">copies:</hi> their activity must be ritual but it is
          not a “liturgy”. The idea of the copy is based on the different
          imaginary which governs the gift of the Law on Mount Sinai and their
          own activity: Moses had received the tables of stone<note n="3" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn3">
              <p>See Shabbat 104a, Sheqalim 6, 49b.</p>
            </note>, so write the scribes on parchment or papyrus scrolls. The
          manner in which the rabbis imagine the episode of the Torah gift is
          highly enlightening as to the manner in which they view the relation
          between “the written” and the act of “writing”.</p>
          <p xml:id="d1e124">We hereby notice that the stakes of “writing” are
          comparable to the stakes of the “written”, of the content, a
          phenomenon which manifests itself in the controversies surrounding
          the original writing of the Tables of the Law. What this denotes is
          an idea of revelation in which the abstract and the material are
          inextricably related. Thus, the question of innovation focuses not
          only on the precepts of the Torah but also and primarily on the
          writing of this. Making not only a “program” but a revealed “graphic
          print” out of the Torah denotes a particular notion of “language as
          a faculty whereby humans express themselves [langage]” and of
          “language as a system of communication [langue]”, as we will see
          later. Here we find ourselves within the clear problematics of
          sacred language.</p>
          <p xml:id="d1e126">In order to illustrate these ideas, I will rely
          on two passages, the Jerusalem Talmud tractate Meguilla and the
          eponymous Babylonian Talmud tractate. The two tractates speak of
          writing and of the language of Revelation in their own way.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="section1" xml:id="d1e128">
          <head subtype="level1" xml:id="d1e129">The Jerusalem Talmud:
          Meguilla 1.9</head>
          <p xml:id="d1e131">How can one explain that Hebrew lost its sacred
          monopoly ? — This is the question that worries Talmudic
          commentators. Indeed Gn 11.1 rightly says, “All the earth had one
          language and used the same words.” According to <persName type="_temp">Rabbi Eliezer</persName>, this meant that people spoke
          the seventy existing languages in full understanding of each other,
          whereas for <persName type="_temp">Rabbi Yohanan</persName> this is
          a reference to “the language of the Unique of the world, the sacred
          language”. The incongruity in relation to the Rabbis’ contemporary
          situation is explained by <persName type="_temp">Bar
          Kappara</persName>, when interpreting the following verse from Gn
          9.27, “God is to extend Japhet’s possessions, he is to live in Sem’s
          tents” as meaning that “we will speak Japhet’s language when in
          Sem’s tent”. Language thus ceases to be a marker of identity and the
          continuation of the Gemara develops a particular notion of the
          nationhood, one which does not connect nation with language but with
          writing. The consequence of this will be to give free hand to
          interpretation and to tighten the regulations of manufacturing.</p>
          <p xml:id="d1e133">The text continues with a functional division of
          languages which are not only supposed to explain but also to
          legitimate multilingualism. By doing that, the Hyerosolomitan Gemara
          undertakes a conceptual and lexical gliding between “language” and
          “writing” :</p>
          <quote rend="quotation" xml:id="d1e135">R. Jonathan de Bet-Gobrin
          says: There are four beautiful languages (<hi rend="italic">lashon</hi>) which are adequate for usage in the
          world, namely: Greek (<hi rend="italic">loaz</hi>) for songs, Latin
          (<hi rend="italic">romi</hi>) for the <hi rend="italic">qerav</hi>
            <note n="4" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn4">
              <p>Word difficult to understand in this context; the proper
              meaning is “battle”. Translations render usually by
              “dispute”.</p>
            </note>, Syrian (<hi rend="italic">sursay</hi>) for elegies,
          Hebrew (<hi rend="italic">ivri</hi>) for speaking (<hi rend="italic">dibbur</hi>).</quote>
          <quote rend="quotation" xml:id="d1e162">Others join the <hi rend="italic">ashuri </hi>for writing. The <hi rend="italic">ashuri</hi> possesses a type of writing but no
          language, whereas Hebrew possesses a language but no type of
          writing. They (the Jews) have chosen <hi rend="italic">ashuri</hi>
          as writing and Hebrew as language. [“Why does this writing bear the
          name <hi rend="italic">ashuri</hi>?” “Because it is substantial (<hi rend="italic">meushar</hi>). According to R. Levi<note n="5" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn5">
              <p>Can this be the disciple of Resh Laqish who lived in the
              third century ?</p>
            </note>, that label reminds one that it has been imported from
          Assyria (<hi rend="italic">Ashur</hi>).”]</quote>
          <p xml:id="d1e187">The word <hi rend="italic">ashuri</hi> designates
          the square letters that were adopted after returning from the first
          Babylonian exile. This is the Aramaic alphabet which replaced the
          ancient so-called Paleo-Hebrew writing, the latter alphabet still
          subsisting in Samaritan writings to the present day. What is
          especially remarkable to note here is that <hi rend="italic">ashuri</hi> was included in a series of “languages”
          (<hi rend="italic">lashon</hi>). The collusion is partly due to the
          fact that Greek, Latin, Syrian and Hebrew are at times “languages”
          and at times “writings”. Nevertheless, they don’t share the sphere
          of the written but that of orality: song, talk, elegy, discourse. In
          order to make sounds visible, Jews “have chosen” signs that are not
          characteristic of their language: “Hebrew has no writing”.
          Simultaneously, <hi rend="italic">ashuri</hi> is not attached to a
          language ; it is free of such conditioning and paves the way to the
          rabbinic hermeneutics of letters. The meaning of its label-name is
          obscure for the rabbis and asks for exegesis: therefore, <hi rend="italic">ashuri</hi> is linked to <hi rend="italic">meushar</hi> (right, substantial) or to <hi rend="italic">Ashur</hi>, Assyria. It is remarkable to note how one
          becomes aware of its “secondary” character in relation to Revelation
          and of the fact that it is a “borrowed” piece of writing. So <hi rend="italic">ashuri</hi> is separated and hence, different from
          both <hi rend="italic">language</hi> and <hi rend="italic">time</hi>
          of Revelation. But if this is the case, the question of the Law
          writing on Mount Sinai gives rise to debates :</p>
          <div type="section2" xml:id="d1e220">
            <head subtype="level2" xml:id="d1e221">First Opinion: the original
            writing of Mount Sinai Revelation was replaced by Esdras</head>
            <quote rend="quotation" xml:id="d1e223">Baraitha<note n="6" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn6">
                <p>Following rabbinical attributions, this is a Baraitha
                dating back to the second century.</p>
              </note> : We have taught that R. Yosse sais : Esdras would have
            deserved to have the Law given by his intermediary if Moses’
            generation had not outdone him. But if the Law was not given by
            his intermediary, he gave “writing” and “language” (<hi rend="italic">ktav ve-lashon</hi>), as it is written : <hi rend="italic">the writing is in Aramaic (katuv aramit) and is
            translated (meturgam) in Aramaic </hi>(Esd 4.7)<note n="7" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn7">
                <p>Here is the verse in context : “And in the time of
                Artaxerxes, Bischlam, Mithredath, Thabeel, and the rest of
                their colleagues wrote to Artaxerxes, king of Persia. The
                letter was transcribed in Aramaic characters and translated in
                Aramaic (<hi rend="italic">katuv aramit u-meturgam
                aramit</hi>).”</p>
              </note>
              <hi rend="italic"> so that they cannot read this
            writing</hi> (Dn 5.8). This proves that it has been replaced<note n="8" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn8">
                <p>“All the king’s sages entered, but they couldn’t read the
                writing and explain its meaning to the king.”</p>
              </note>.</quote>
            <p xml:id="d1e248">This first opinion on the gift of “writing”
            once again relates it to “language”. By contrast to preceding
            assertions about the <hi rend="italic">ashuri</hi>, here,
            <persName type="_temp">Rabbi Yosse</persName> clearly identifies
            it with Aramaic as “language and writing”. The mediator of the
            “writing” is Esdras, the “second Moses” in rabbinic literature.
            Credit is generally given to Esdras for the invention of the <hi rend="italic">targum</hi>, cantillation and exegesis. But if the
            word <hi rend="italic">aramit</hi> at times designates “language”
            and “writing”, this means that the Law was written in <hi rend="italic">aramit</hi>, i.e. in square characters, and the
            translation, <hi rend="italic">targum</hi>, was also in Aramaic.
            In order to discard any misunderstanding, a second verse is
            invoked for support: in Belshatzar’s post-Revelation time, an
            epoch described by <hi rend="italic">Daniel</hi>, “writing” wasn’t
            understood. The impossibility to understand “writing” thus proves
            its novelty and the fact that it has been only recently received,
            in postexilic times, through Esdras mediation.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="section2" xml:id="d1e269">
            <head subtype="level2" xml:id="d1e270">Second opinion: Mount Sinai
            Revelation was given in intermingled writing</head>
            <quote rend="quotation" xml:id="d1e272">R. Gamaliel<note n="9" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn9">
                <p>Probably Galamiel II, at the end of the first and the
                beginning of the second century.</p>
              </note> says : The Law was promulgated in a piece of writing
            using intermingled letters (<hi rend="italic">raats</hi>). The
            opinion conforms to that of R. Yosse.</quote>
            <p xml:id="d1e281">
              <persName type="_temp">Rabbi
            Gamaliel</persName> not only confirms the gift of Esdras’ writing
            with square letters but also specifies that the original writing
            consisted of “intermingled” characters. We cannot know if the
            Rabbi’s interpretation refers to what we call today Paleo-Hebrew
            writing but the evolution of the Revelation leaves room for
            understanding an interesting aspect of the rabbinical historical
            imaginary, the manner in which they conceived the ideas of
            evolution and progress.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="section2" xml:id="d1e283">
            <head subtype="level2" xml:id="d1e284">Third opinion : Mount Sinai
            Revelation was given in <hi rend="italic">ashuri</hi>
            </head>
            <quote rend="quotation" xml:id="d1e288">According to Rabbi<note n="10" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn10">
                <p>Rabbi Juda the Prince, second and third centuries.</p>
              </note>, it was delivered in <hi rend="italic">ashuri</hi>
            writing; when Israel sinned, the writing got converted in
            intermingled characters and when it later became virtuous again,
            under Esdras, the characters also became <hi rend="italic">ashuri</hi> once again. As it is said: <hi rend="italic">Today do I declare that I will give you</hi>
              <hi rend="italic">the double (mishneh) </hi>(Za 9.12<note n="11" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn11">
                <p>“Go back to the fortress, captives full of hope! I declare
                it today once again; I will give you the double (<hi rend="italic">mishneh ashiv lekha</hi>)”.</p>
              </note>) and also:<hi rend="italic"> he will write him a double
            (mishneh) of that Law on a book </hi>(Dt 17.18)<note n="12" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn12">
                <p>“When he climbs to the royal throne, he will have to write
                a copy of that Law on a scroll for his usage and under
                dictation from the Levite priests (<hi rend="italic">ve-ktav
                lo et-mishneh ha-torah ha-zot al sefer</hi>).”</p>
              </note> ; this is an allusion to a form of writing prone to
            changes.</quote>
            <p xml:id="d1e324">The third opinion belonging to the Rabbi
            connects the gift of writing to the general scheme of Jewish
            history : sin and expiation of sins. In this case, Esdras is no
            longer the civilizing hero but only the <hi rend="italic">réparateur</hi>. He does not receive the
            Writing/Scripture per se but “a double”. Rabbi, the one to whom
            this thesis is attributed, interprets the word <hi rend="italic">mishneh</hi>, “double”, not as an identical copy but
            as a “second” revelation. And as it is inconceivable to receive a
            “new” Law, the only possible change is related to “writing”. So
            Rabbi does not accept to make Esdras the mediator of “canonical”
            writing, <hi rend="italic">ashuri</hi>; this attitude obliges him
            to force his biblical proof texts by introducing an understatement
            in the interpretation he gives to the word <hi rend="italic">mishneh</hi>, “double, second”. He chooses to
            consider the “second” not as being “identical” but as being
            “modifiable” and as “modified”. The material aspects are
            sufficiently important to represent the object of a punishment
            that would equate to a form of divine silence : writing becomes
            “intermingled”. Meanwhile, writing with square letters, a precious
            good, is removed from the Jewish people up to the time of
            Esdras.</p>
            <p xml:id="d1e338">After exposing these three possibilities, the
            Talmudic passage develops its arguments in one way or another.
            Thus, the Rabbi’s opinion finds support in a Tannaitic dictum (a
            Baraitha) :</p>
            <quote rend="quotation" xml:id="d1e340">It was taught that Rabbi
            Simon ben Eliezer<note n="13" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn13">
                <p>A colleague of Rabbi. But the Baraitha dates back the chain
                of transmission up to Eliezer ben Modai, dead in 134.</p>
              </note> says in the name of R. Eliezer ben Parta and this one in
            the name of R. Eliezer ben Modai: the Law must have been written
            in <hi rend="italic">ashuri </hi>characters. What is the proof ?
            <hi rend="italic">The vav-s [are] columns (amudim)</hi> (Ex
            27.10<note n="14" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn14">
                <p>The literal sense of the verse is the following : “The
                hooks of columns (<hi rend="italic">vavei
                ha-amudim</hi>)”.</p>
              </note>) ; thus the vav-s in the Law must be straight as a
            column (<hi rend="italic">amud</hi>).</quote>
            <p xml:id="d1e362">Since the letter “vav” in <hi rend="italic">ashuri</hi> square script ressembles a column, it
            means that the script could not have been intermingled (<hi rend="italic">raatz</hi>) characters. The shape of the letters
            becomes an argument in point of reconstituting the history of the
            Revelation. In any case, the miracle is necessary :</p>
            <quote rend="quotation" xml:id="d1e370">Rabbi Levi said: According
            to those for whom the Law was given in intermingled characters,
            one is to deduct that the <hi rend="italic">ayn</hi> held by
            miracle: and according to those who sustain that the Law was given
            in <hi rend="italic">ashuri</hi> characters, one is to deduct that
            the <hi rend="italic">samekh</hi> equally held by a similar
            miracle. Rabbi Jeremiah<note n="15" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn15">
                <p>A Palestinian Rabbi from the fourth century, born in
                Babylonia and subsequently the chief of the Academy of
                Tiberias.</p>
              </note>, in the name of Rabbi Hyya bar Ba<note n="16" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn16">
                <p>Active at the end of the third century (cca 270-300).</p>
              </note> and of Rabbi Simon Terihon, says: in the original Torah
            there was no <hi rend="italic">he</hi> nor any closed <hi rend="italic">mem</hi> but only a closed <hi rend="italic">samekh</hi>.<note n="17" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn17">
                <p>Because their form is similar to a closed circle.</p>
              </note>
            </quote>
            <p xml:id="d1e402">In the rabbinic imaginary the Tables of the Law
            are so inscribed that they can be read both ways. If the signs are
            not universally visible it is because they are not drawn but they
            are carved. Such letters as the <hi rend="italic">intermingled</hi>
              <hi rend="italic">ayn</hi> or the
            <hi rend="italic">ashuri samekh</hi> come up to the circumference
            of a circle without being attached to the mass of the Table. It is
            the reification of a vacuum, even the abstraction of a form. Only
            a miracle can explain their subsistence on the Tables of Law.</p>
            <p xml:id="d1e413">The role of the miracle for the material
            consistence of the Torah is developed in the Babylonian tractate
            Meguilla, in a later passage from the fourth century. If
            previously the connection between form and content was operated by
            means of the bias of language, in this case the connection is
            operated by means of analysing the principle of innovation (<hi rend="italic">hidush</hi>).</p>
          </div>
          <div type="section2" xml:id="d1e418">
            <head subtype="level2" xml:id="d1e419">Babylonian Talmud :
            Meguilla 2b-3a</head>
            <quote rend="quotation" xml:id="d1e421">Rabbi Jeremiah (or,
            according to others, Rabbi Hyya ben Abba) said : The final forms
            of letters <hi rend="italic">mem</hi>, <hi rend="italic">nun</hi>,
            <hi rend="italic">tsadek</hi>, <hi rend="italic">peh</hi>, <hi rend="italic">kaph</hi>, had been “told” by the watchmen.</quote>
            <quote rend="quotation" xml:id="d1e438">Is what you believe
            right ? Isn’t it written <hi rend="italic">These are the
            commandments</hi> (Lv 27.34), which implies that no prophet is
            authorized to introduce anything new? Moreover, Rabbi Hisda<note n="18" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn18">
                <p>A Babylonian Rabbi at the end of the third and the
                beginning of the fourth century.</p>
              </note> added that: <hi rend="italic">the mem</hi> and <hi rend="italic">the samekh</hi> have guarded their place on the
            Tables of the Law by miracle<note n="19" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn19">
                <p>Because their form is similar to a closed circle.</p>
              </note>.</quote>
            <quote rend="quotation" xml:id="d1e457">Here is how it happened :
            (These letters) were in use but the people didn’t know what form
            to put in the middle of the word and what form to place at the end
            of the word ; thus, the Watchmen established that open forms will
            be used in the middle and closed forms at the end. Yet, after all
            was <hi rend="underline">said and done</hi>, one thing was left,
            the text that <hi rend="italic">These are the commandments</hi>,
            implying that no prophet had the right to introduce anything new
            afterwards. We must then understand that the letters had been <hi rend="underline">forgotten</hi> and the Watchmen restored
            them.</quote>
            <p xml:id="d1e468">In the Babylonian version the controversy no
            longer relates to the Jewish civilizing hero, Moses versus Esdras,
            but the basis of consensus is the gift of the Torah on Mount Sinai
            which was written in square letters. Yet the controversy is
            centred on the open and closed form of certain letters. Rabbi
            Jeremiah attributes them to the Watchmen, a term used to designate
            the prophets that succeeded Moses. Introducing something new, be
            it only on the level of form, nevertheless equates to
            transgressing the Deuteronomic verse at the end of the Revelation.
            The Watchmen’s role thus needs to be delimited more clearly : in a
            first variant, they only put order in <hi rend="italic">the use of
            form</hi> without creating that form themselves; in a second
            variant, they <hi rend="italic">restored</hi> the previously <hi rend="italic">forgotten</hi> forms. Rabbis usually solve the
            tension between the novelty and closure of the Revelation by the
            bias of the anamnesis. This is also the case of Targum, the
            Aramaic version of the Bible, to give one example, which was also
            “forgotten and restored” (Meguilla 3a). The same artifice of
            restoring the forgotten is part of the Christian thematics of the
            Adamic language to which Maurice Olender has dedicated some of his
            studies<note n="20" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn20">
                <p>Olender 1989.</p>
              </note>.</p>
            <p xml:id="d1e483">It should also be noted that the completion of
            the Tables of the Law finds expression in the phrase “all was said
            and done” : word and gesture, abstraction and materiality conjoin
            together to make the Law. Both are subject to canonicity and they
            are hermeneutic aims.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section1" xml:id="d1e485">
          <head subtype="level1" xml:id="d1e486">Practical Rules</head>
          <p xml:id="d1e488">Having highlighted the etiological imaginary of
          writing and its implications on the definition of a textual
          community, let us go on to examine the normative imaginary related
          to the writing of the Torah scrolls. I talk voluntarily of imaginary
          since, as Judith Schlanger has proved it in her intervention on “La
          mise en texte: écriture, pensée, lecture”<note n="21" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn21">
              <p>The lecture was delivered during the Study Days organized by
              Christian Jacob within this GDRI convention, entitled « Les
              mondes lettrés », and held on October 13-14, 2006.</p>
            </note>, there is no genuine kosher scroll. The enquiry over texts
          can’t establish the degree of applicability for the norms, nor can
          it establish if they can be applied selectively or what are the
          means to go round the norms, or what are the agreed limits allowing
          for scribal transgression.</p>
          <p xml:id="d1e494">As I have already specified in the introduction,
          the commandments (<hi rend="italic">mitzvot</hi>) related to the
          fabrication of scrolls are codified in the tractate <hi rend="italic">Meguilla</hi> as well as in a subsequent post-Talmudic
          tractate, <hi rend="italic">Sopherim</hi>. Without making the claim
          for an exhaustive and systematic analysis of these instructions, I
          will only enumerate some prescriptions that invite one to reflection
          in relation to the topic chosen for the present debate and having to
          do with what I have called “the reification” of the text and the
          letter.</p>
          <div type="section2" xml:id="d1e505">
            <head subtype="level2" xml:id="d1e506">Requisites for
            Sacredness</head>
            <p xml:id="d1e508">Let us start with the fundamental passage of
            Mishna Meguilla in which the confusion between “language” and
            “writing” leaves room for a long discussion bearing on the
            prohibitions related to translation and the prohibitions related
            to transliteration :</p>
            <quote rend="quotation" xml:id="d1e510">Mishna : There is no
            difference between books [of the Bible] and <hi rend="italic">tefillin</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mezuzah</hi>
            save that the books [of the Bible] may be written in any language
            (<hi rend="italic">kol lashon</hi>) while <hi rend="italic">tefillin</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mezuzah</hi> can
            only be written in <hi rend="italic">ashuri</hi>. Rabban Simeon
            ben Gamaliel says : “For the books [of the Bible] we haven’t
            authorized any other <hi rend="italic">language</hi>, with the
            exception of <hi rend="italic">Greek</hi>.” (Meguilla 8b)</quote>
            <p xml:id="d1e537">To that the Babylonian Gemara opposes a
            Tannaitic tradition (Baraitha) which implies a contradiction with
            the Mishna :</p>
            <quote rend="quotation" xml:id="d1e539">[A Scriptural scroll
            containing] a Hebrew text written in <hi rend="italic">targum</hi>
            (Aramaic) or an Aramaic text written in Hebrew, or [either] in
            Hebraic script does not defile the hands ; [it does not do so]
            until it is written in <hi rend="italic">ashuri</hi> script upon a
            scroll and in ink’ ! (Meguilla 8b)</quote>
            <p xml:id="d1e547">This permanent to and from movement between
            signifier and signified, between form and content, is far from
            illuminating the meaning ; on the contrary, it makes it more and
            more ambiguous. How is one to understand the phrase <hi rend="italic">katuv be-aramit </hi>? <hi rend="italic">Katuv
            </hi>can designate the Scripture as well as something “written”.
            Similarly, the word <hi rend="italic">aramit</hi> can designate
            either the square alphabet or the Aramaic language, hence another
            confusion, that between Aramaic texts of the Bible and the <hi rend="italic">targum</hi>, the Aramaic translation of the Bible.
            The rabbis of the Talmud try to solve this total imbroglio,
            especially since it is the case of a ritual context, that of
            making manuscripts that are ritually appropriate.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="section2" xml:id="d1e561">
            <head subtype="level2" xml:id="d1e562">The Concern over Formal
            Clarity</head>
            <p xml:id="d1e564">The fear of “non-distinction”, of non-identity
            of the “mixed letter”, is another topos underlying the conditions
            of sacredness. We cannot write a letter as another : the <hi rend="italic">alef</hi> as an <hi rend="italic">ayn</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">beth</hi> as a <hi rend="italic">kaf</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">kaf</hi> as a <hi rend="italic">beth</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">gimmel</hi> as a <hi rend="italic">tsaddek</hi> and
            <hi rend="italic">t</hi>
              <hi rend="italic">saddek</hi> as <hi rend="italic">gimmel</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">daleth</hi> as a
            <hi rend="italic">resh</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">resh</hi> as a
            <hi rend="italic">daleth</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">he</hi> as a
            <hi rend="italic">heth</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">heth</hi> as a
            <hi rend="italic">he</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">vav</hi> as a <hi rend="italic">yod</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">yod</hi> as a <hi rend="italic">vav</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">zayin</hi> as a <hi rend="italic">nun</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">nun</hi> as a <hi rend="italic">zayin</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">teth</hi> as a <hi rend="italic">peh</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">peh</hi> as a <hi rend="italic">teth</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">mem</hi> as a <hi rend="italic">samekh</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">samekh</hi> as a
            <hi rend="italic">mem</hi>, the closed letters as open letters and
            the open letters as closed ones (Shabbat 103b).</p>
            <p xml:id="d1e675">At the same time, each letter has to be <hi rend="italic">surrounded by parchment</hi> as there shouldn’t be
            any overlapping. Here we find the imaginary of the Tables of the
            Law and of writing with intermingled letters corresponding to the
            sin of Israel.</p>
            <p xml:id="d1e680">The text is never completely interdependent on
            the idea of support. The letter is very material in its graphic
            trajectory while it is also an abstract entity which does not make
            one body with the parchment. In what regards this topic, here is
            an example of Talmudic questioning: can we use the blank space
            between blocks of writing? The debate is part of the Babylonian
            Talmud Shabbat 116a:</p>
            <quote rend="quotation" xml:id="d1e682">But why so conclude [that
            we must save it] on account of its blank space? As for the place
            of the writing, I have no doubt, for when it was sanctified it was
            on account of the writing, [and] when its writing goes its
            sanctity goes [too]. My problem is only in respect of [the blank
            spaces] above and below, between the sections, between the
            columns, [and] at the beginning and the end of the Scroll. Yet
            conclude [that it must be saved] on that account? It may mean
            [there] that one had cut off [the blank spaces] and thrown them
            away.</quote>
          </div>
          <div type="section2" xml:id="d1e684">
            <head subtype="level2" xml:id="d1e685">The Embellishment of
            Letters</head>
            <p xml:id="d1e687">The embellishment of certain letters in the
            square alphabet also raises questions as to the consubstantiality
            between the letter and the ornament – <hi rend="italic">tagin</hi>
            in Aramaic, <hi rend="italic">ketarim</hi> in Hebrew,
            “wreaths”. </p>
            <p xml:id="d1e695">The commandment of the <hi rend="italic">zyunin</hi>
              <note n="22" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn22">
                <p>This comes from the letter <hi rend="italic">zayin</hi>, a
                letter to which resemble the three decoration lines that form
                a set, a <hi rend="italic">taga</hi> or a <hi rend="italic">keter</hi>, “wreath”. <hi rend="italic">Zyun</hi> is also translated by “armour”.</p>
              </note> is introduced by Rava in the Gemara Menahot 29b: Rava
            says that there are seven letters, each of which requires three
            <hi rend="italic">tagin</hi>: <hi rend="italic">shin</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ayn</hi>, <hi rend="italic">teth</hi>, <hi rend="italic">nun</hi>, <hi rend="italic">zayin</hi>, <hi rend="italic">gimmel</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">tzaddeh</hi>.
            These ornaments will be integrated in the tradition and will form
            the focus of rabbinic discussions throughout the entire history of
            Judaism. The tradition also reports a book entitled <hi rend="italic">Sefer ha-tagin</hi>
              <note n="23" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn23">
                <p>Copied by Simha ben Samuel, Rachi’s disciple, in his Mahzor
                Vitry. An adnotated edition was made by Senior Sachs in
                1866.</p>
              </note>. The picture below, not reproducing a biblical
            manuscript from the Talmudic epoch since we don’t possess one, is
            meant to give an image of the manner in which tradition has used
            those <hi rend="italic">tagin</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ketarim</hi>.</p>
            <figure xml:id="d1e753">
              <graphic url="https://didomena.ehess.fr/downloads/c821gk60n.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <p xml:id="d1e757">How does the Talmud reason over the importance
            of ornaments ? The following aetiology can be found in Menahot
            29b :</p>
            <quote rend="quotation" xml:id="d1e759">Rav Juda says in Rav’s
            name : “When Moses climbed high up, he found the Unique One, May
            He Be Blessed, who was in the process of placing wreathes on the
            letters.” Moses : “Master of the Universe, who holds up Your
            hand ?” He answered: “Many generations from now, there will be a
            man named Akiba ben Joseph who will interpret each wreath of the
            Law’s letters.” “Master of the Universe, let me see him.” “Turn
            around !” Moses went eight steps down and listened to the
            discussions about the Law. Not being able to understand them, he
            felt uncomfortable. But when they reached a certain topic and the
            disciples asked, “How come you know that ?” and the other’s
            response was “It was given to Moses on Mount Sinai”, he felt
            better. Then, he turned back toward God : “Master of the Universe,
            You have such a man and you give the Torah through me ?” And God
            answered : “Be silent. This is my decision.”</quote>
            <quote rend="quotation" xml:id="d1e761">Rab Judah said in the name
            of Rab: “When Moses ascended on high he found the Holy One,
            blessed be He, engaged in affixing coronets to the letters. Said
            Moses : ‘Lord of the Universe, Who stays Thy hand ?’ He answered :
            ‘There will arise a man, at the end of many generations, Akiba b.
            Joseph by name, who will expound upon each tittle heaps and heaps
            of laws’. ‘Lord of the Universe’, said Moses, ‘permit me to see
            him’. He replied, ‘Turn thee round’. Moses went and sat down
            behind eight rows [and listened to the discourses upon the law].
            Not being able to follow their arguments he was ill at ease, but
            when they came to a certain subject and the disciples said to the
            master ‘Whence do you know it ?’ and the latter replied ‘It is a
            law given unto Moses at Sinai’ he was comforted. Thereupon he
            returned to the Holy One, blessed be He, and said, ‘Lord of the
            Universe, Thou hast such a man and Thou givest the Torah by me !’
            He replied, ‘Be silent, for such is My decree’.</quote>
            <p xml:id="d1e763">God in the position of a scribe did not give
            the Torah only in words, but also revealed it in its materiality.
            The “wreaths” are the work of a divinity for which the superfluous
            does not exist. Everything has a hermeneutic value, even the
            letter ornaments. Moses considers the operation as of no interest,
            especially on the part of God, and he even admits he is unworthy
            of receiving the Torah. The subtle truth of the revelation is
            Rabbi Akiba who will discover it. Tradition and innovation face
            one another through details. Their importance is disclosed in
            numerous Talmudic discussions. The Shabbat 104b-105a tract, for
            instance, considers that those who write the letters without <hi rend="italic">tagin</hi> on a shabbat day do not violate the
            interdiction to write on a day of shabbat. These signs therefore
            are an integral part of letters<note n="24" place="foot" type="standard" xml:id="ftn24">
                <p>Subsequent commentators haven’t reached any consensus in
                this regard: some of them will argue in favour of essential
                elements, others won’t. Among the reasons that have been
                invoked is that of ensuring the “square” character of these
                letters and that of avoiding their round character.</p>
              </note>.</p>
            <p xml:id="d1e772">This entire array of practical rules describes
            the double process of strictly regulated fabrication, on the one
            hand, and the freedom of interpretation, on the other hand.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div type="section1" xml:id="d1e774">
          <head subtype="level1" xml:id="d1e775">Conclusions</head>
          <p xml:id="d1e777">To what problematics do the texts presented here
          direct us, given that their characteristic feature is the
          establishment of an equivalence between “writing” and “language” and
          well as the establishment of the dialectics of “form” and
          “content” ?</p>
          <p xml:id="d1e779">Obviously, the implicit notion under debate is
          that of “language as a faculty whereby humans express themselves
          [<hi rend="italic">langage</hi>]” which, in its turn, includes the
          idea of language as a system of communication [<hi rend="italic">langue</hi>] and sacred tongue. Studies by both
          antiquarians and modernists generally tend to consider language as
          the national mark of identity <hi rend="italic">par excellence</hi>.
          This is also true of Jewish studies and in this sense I can refer to
          at least two authors: Seth Schwartz and Milka Levy-Rubin. The former
          defines Hebrew as a “national symbol” during the first two centuries
          of our era (Schwartz, 2005) ; the latter looks over the ancient
          Jewish texts which make Hebrew the language of Creation and
          Revelation in view of the same revival of national ideology during
          the Hasmonean era (Levy-Rubin, 1998). Yet the passages we have
          analysed do not bring forth a “linguistic community” but an
          “alphabetic community”.</p>
          <p xml:id="d1e790">To my knowledge, this phenomenon hasn’t been
          observed before and its potential impact hasn’t been considered. I
          would be very much tempted to re-open for debate the historiographic
          hypothesis exposed or, at least, to reconsider it by taking into
          consideration the importance attributed to writing in the Mishna and
          the Talmud.</p>
          <p xml:id="d1e792">The indices of this “alphabetic community” appear
          for the first time in the Mishna : this chronological aspect
          deserves attention because one has to understand it as a mutation in
          point of the manner used to define itself as an identity (but whose
          character remains to be specified : religious ? ethnic ?
          national ?).</p>
          <p xml:id="d1e794">As an example of historical contextualisation of
          the use of writing, the works of Clarisse Herrenschmidt tackle
          aspects entirely compatible with those in our portfolio. In her
          article, “Le Tout, l’Énigme et l’Illusion », published in <hi rend="italic">Le Débat </hi>in 1990, she examines the
          anthropological scope of three types of writing : the graphical
          “whole” of the wedge-shaped, the enigma of the Hebrew consonantal
          alphabet, and the illusion of the entirely decontextualised Greek
          alphabet. The author says that “the various writings don’t establish
          the same type of graphic connection between <hi rend="underline">the
          things of language</hi> and <hi rend="underline">the things of the
          world</hi>. […] This happens because every piece of writing
          establishes a certain relationship between its user and the world ;
          by telling the world in the written the user invades, explores and
          at times transforms the intrinsic possibilities of his graphic
          print.”</p>
          <p xml:id="d1e805">Of the three graphic strategies analysed in the
          article, that of the Persian Empire is the most relevant one for our
          interest here. Certainly, the interpretation given to the graphic
          strategy of the Hebrew people, for whom writing is an integral part
          of the revelation and each written word a consonantal enigma whose
          sense is clarified only in context, seems to me always
          pertinent.</p>
          <p xml:id="d1e807">Yet, the solution found by the Achemenid Persians
          in what regards imperial multilingualism sheds light on the
          portfolio we have presented here. It is in Achemenid Persian that we
          find the most significant development of trilingual royal
          inscriptions, the Great King having the super-human power of
          multilingualism. “In the chain of the written necessary for the
          empire, the Persian language has functioned as a game of
          hide-and-seek, under several linguistic-graphic masks.” The
          consequence : “The graphic Whole characterising the wedge-shaped
          world has imploded: there was no longer a union between the written,
          language and the world, but language became autonomous in and
          through the indifferentiation of language; from now on, language
          belongs to the Interpreter who achieves it beyond languages and
          writings.” “The indifference of language which tells the world to
          the language which makes it, the indifferences of men to the
          language they write in order to say the world. » (Herrenschmidt
          1990, p. 107)</p>
          <p xml:id="d1e809">Jewish bilingualism and multilingualism finally
          raise similar questions, while at the same time pointing to the
          unprecedented importance given to graphic signs.</p>
          <p xml:id="d1e811">Just as the Persian king is the guarantor of
          truth beyond languages, the Torah is the word of truth beyond its
          linguistic particularism.</p>
          <p xml:id="d1e813">Finally, it might be that for the rabbis this is
          an instance of securing a counterbalance to the other grand theme of
          their ideology : orality. The authority of the Rabbi’s / Torah
          interpreter’s oral statement is counterbalanced by the uniformity of
          writing.</p>
          <p xml:id="d1e816">The texts constituting the Jewish tradition
          deserve being rethought in light of studies that focus on
          writing.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="bibliographie" xml:id="d1e819">
        <head xml:id="d1e820">Bibliography</head>
        <listBibl xml:id="d1e822">
          <bibl xml:id="d1e823">
            <hi rend="small-caps">Blank</hi> Debra Reed,
          1995, « It’s time to take another look at our “little sister”
          Soferim : a bibliographical essay », <hi rend="italic">Conservative
          Judaism</hi>, 48/1, p. 10.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="d1e830">
            <hi rend="small-caps">Briant </hi>Pierre, <hi rend="italic">Histoire de l’Empire perse. De Cyrus à Alexandre</hi>,
          Paris, 1996, p. 535-536.<hi rend="small-caps"/>
          </bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="d1e839">
            <hi rend="small-caps">Herrenschmidt</hi>
          Clarisse, 1990, « Le Tout, l’Énigme et l’Illusion. Une
          interprétation de l’histoire de l’écriture », <hi rend="italic">Le
          Débat</hi>, 62, p. 95-118.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="d1e846">
            <hi rend="small-caps">Heide</hi> Albert van
          der, 2006, « “Mem and samekh” stood by a miracle : the sugya on the
          Hebrew script (Shabbat 103a-104a) », <hi rend="italic">Studia
          Rosenthaliana</hi> 38-39, p. 137-143.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="d1e853">
            <hi rend="small-caps">Herrenschmidt</hi>
          Clarisse, 1996, « L’écriture entre mondes visible et invisible », in
          J. Bottéro, Cl. Herrenschmidt, J.-P. Vernant (éds), <hi rend="italic">L’Orient Ancien et Nous. L’écriture, la raison, les
          dieux</hi>, Paris, p. 95-188.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="d1e860">
            <hi rend="small-caps">Levy-Rubin</hi> Milka,
          1998, « The language of Creation or the primordial language: a case
          of cultural polemics in antiquity », <hi rend="italic">Journal of
          Jewish Studies</hi>, 49/2, p. 306-333.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="d1e867">
            <hi rend="small-caps">Macdonald </hi>M. C. A.,
          2006, « Literacy in an Oral Environment », in P. Bienkowski, Ch.
          Mee, E. Slater (éds), <hi rend="italic">Writing and Ancient Near
          Eastern Society. Papers in Honour of Alan R. Millard</hi>, New York,
          p. 49-118.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="d1e874">
            <hi rend="small-caps">Olender</hi> Maurice,
          1989, <hi rend="italic">Les langues du paradis. Aryens et Sémites :
          un couple providentie</hi>,<hi rend="italic"/>Paris.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="d1e884">
            <hi rend="small-caps">Olender</hi> Maurice,
          1993, « Europe, or how to escape Babel », in A. Grafton et S.L.
          Marchand (éds),<hi rend="italic"> Proof and persuasion</hi>,
          Wesleyan U. P.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="d1e891">
            <hi rend="small-caps">Root</hi> M., 1997,
          « Cultural Pluralisms and the Persepolis Fortification Tablets »,
          <hi rend="italic">Topoi</hi> Suppl. 1, p. 229-252.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="d1e898">
            <hi rend="small-caps">Schwartz</hi> Seth,
          2005, « Language, power and identity in ancient Palestine », in
          C. Bakhos (éd.), <hi rend="italic">Ancient Judaism in Its
          Hellenistic Context</hi>, Leiden, p. 52-84.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="d1e906">
            <hi rend="small-caps">Sirat</hi> Colette,
          1991, « Les rouleaux bibliques de Qumrân au Moyen Âge : du Livre au
          Sefer Tora, de l’oreille à l’œil », Académie des Inscriptions et
          Belles-Lettres : Comptes Rendus (avril-juin 1991),
          p. 415-432.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="d1e910">
            <hi rend="small-caps">Sirat</hi> Colette,
          1997, « Orality/literacy, language and alphabets: examples of the
          Jewish people », in Clotilde Pontecorvo (éd.), <hi rend="italic">Writing Development; an Interdisciplinary View</hi>,
          Amsterdam, Philadelphia, p. 101-115.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="d1e917">
            <hi rend="small-caps">Sirat</hi> Colette,
          1998, « Les lettres hébraïques, leur existence idéale et
          matérielle », in A. L. Ivry, E. R. Wolfson, A. Arkush (éds), <hi rend="italic">Perspectives on Jewish Thought and Mysticism;
          Dedicated to the Memory of Alexander Altmann</hi>, Amsterdam,
          p. 237-256.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="d1e924">
            <hi rend="small-caps">Taragin</hi> Moshe
          (Rav), « The Crowns of the Hebrew Script », in <hi rend="italic">Talmudic Methodology</hi>, Yeshivat Har Etzion –
          Israel Koschnitzky Virtual Beit Midrash, <ref target="http://www.vbm-torah.org/archive/metho60/05taggin.doc">http://www.vbm-torah.org/archive/metho60/05taggin.doc</ref>.</bibl>
          <bibl xml:id="d1e934">
            <hi rend="small-caps">Veltri </hi>Giuseppe,
          2002, « Tradent und Traditum im antiken Judentum », in <hi rend="italic">Id</hi>., <hi rend="italic">Gegenwart der
          Tradition</hi>, Leiden, p. 3-27.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>